In the last video, we created constraints so that we can drive the muscles with an animated skeleton.
지난 영상에서는 애니메이션된 스켈레톤으로 근육을 구동할 수 있도록 구속(Constraint)을 만들었습니다.
And we ran a simulation with that, you can see, but we noticed that the wrist is a little bit falling off.
그 상태로 시뮬레이션을 돌려보니 보시는 것처럼 손목 쪽이 약간 이탈하는 문제가 보이네요.
So let's go ahead and increase the radius here so that we have more kinematic constraints.
그래서 여기 반경을 키워서 키네마틱 구속을 더 많이 걸어주겠습니다.
So let's change that from 0.5 to 0.8.
값을 0.5에서 0.8로 바꿔볼게요.
Now we're ready to paint on muscle origin insertions.
이제 근육의 기시/정지(Origin/Insertion)를 페인팅할 준비가 됐습니다.
Muscle origin insertions, they are muscle attachments to bones.
기시/정지는 근육이 뼈에 붙는 지점을 뜻합니다.
So basically think about the bicep here.
예를 들어 여기 상완이두근(바이셉)을 떠올려 보세요.
The muscle origin will be the one closer to the root.
근육의 기시는 루트에 더 가까운 쪽입니다.
And then muscle insertion will be the one far further away from the root.
그리고 근육의 정지는 루트에서 더 멀리 떨어진 쪽이죠.
So let's go ahead and bring in the sculptal mesh muscles so we can paint on it.
이제 페인팅할 수 있도록 스켈레탈 메시에 있는 근육들을 불러오겠습니다.
Let's grab the muscles.
근육들을 선택해 올리고,
And again, let's convert this to a sculptal mesh collection.
다시 이것을 스켈레탈 메시 컬렉션으로 변환하겠습니다.
And now at this point, we can just click this paint weight map node to start painting on it.
이제 여기서 Paint Weight Map 노드를 눌러서 바로 페인팅을 시작할 수 있어요.
And for the attribute, let's call this one origin.
속성(Attribute) 이름은 origin으로 하겠습니다.
We'll use two muscles as an example.
예시로 근육 두 개만 사용해 볼게요.
First, let's use the left lower pectoralis.
먼저 왼쪽 하부 대흉근을 써보겠습니다.
See, we'll have the painting tool here.
여기에 페인팅 도구가 보이네요.
Let's go ahead and use poly lasso.
폴리 라쏘(Poly Lasso)를 사용하겠습니다.
I think it looks good.
좋아 보입니다.
Because we're painting on the origin, be a little careful and draw the attachments.
지금은 기시를 칠하고 있으니, 부착 부위를 너무 넓히지 않도록 주의해서 그려 주세요.
Looks pretty good.
괜찮네요.
Also, let's paint it on the bicep.
이두근에도 페인팅해 줍니다.
That's a good amount.
이 정도 양이면 적당합니다.
Now let's do the same thing for insertion.
이제 같은 방식으로 정지도 작업해 봅시다.
Let's work on the same muscles.
방금 작업한 같은 근육들에 대해 진행하겠습니다.
The reason that we're painting on the sculptal mesh instead of on the tetrahedral mesh is that
우리가 사면체 메시가 아니라 스켈레탈 메시에 페인팅하는 이유는,
the sculptal mesh is not changing.
스켈레탈 메시는 토폴로지가 바뀌지 않기 때문입니다.
We're not changing this topology, but we could potentially change the topology of the tetrahedral
스켈레탈 메시 토폴로지는 그대로지만,
mesh.
사면체 메시의 토폴로지는 변경될 수도 있거든요.
So, once we paint on the sculptal mesh, we can always transfer
그래서 스켈레탈 메시에 먼저 칠해 두면,
painting from the sculptal mesh to the tetrahedral mesh.
그 페인트를 스켈레탈 메시에서 사면체 메시에 언제든 전송(Transfer)할 수 있습니다.
So, let's go ahead and do that right now.
지금 바로 그렇게 해 보죠.
Call this transfer vertex attribute node.
Transfer Vertex Attribute 노드를 추가합니다.
And make sure you connect from collection and also the attribute key.
그리고 From Collection과 Attribute Key를 잊지 말고 연결하세요.
We're going to do the same thing for insertions as well.
정지(insertion)도 같은 방식으로 한 번 더 해 줍니다.
By the way, inside this transfer vertex attribute node here,
참고로 이 Transfer Vertex Attribute 노드 안을 보면
you can see we have different transfer modes.
여러 가지 전송 모드가 있습니다.
In this case, we have an exact one-to-one match between the sculptal mesh geometry
이번에는 스켈레탈 메시 지오메트리와 사면체 메시 지오메트리가
and the tetrahedral mesh geometry.
서로 정확히 1:1로 대응합니다.
So, in this case, we can use paired geometry transfer.
이럴 때는 Paired Geometry Transfer를 쓰면 됩니다.
Otherwise, we should use a global transfer.
그게 아니라면 Global Transfer를 사용해야 합니다.
Basically, it's a global transfer by proximity.
쉽게 말해, Global Transfer는 근접도 기반의 전역 전송 방식입니다.
So, let's go ahead and use paired geometry.
이번에는 Paired Geometry를 사용하겠습니다.
So, you can see whatever is in white, they're being transferred right now.
하얗게 표시되는 영역이 지금 전송되고 있는 부분입니다.
Same thing for insertions.
정지도 같은 방식으로요.
You should be able to see the bicep here.
여기 이두근에서도 확인할 수 있습니다.
There.
네, 보이죠.
That's the transfer result.
이게 전송 결과입니다.
And that's good.
좋습니다.
Let's go ahead and start extracting origin and insertion vertices.
이제 기시와 정지에 해당하는 버텍스를 추출해 보겠습니다.
Let's call vertex scalar.
Vertex Scalar → Vertex Indices 노드를 사용합니다.
To vertex indices.
버텍스 인덱스로 변환하죠.
And for attribute.
그리고 Attribute는
Let's connect the attribute key.
Attribute Key를 연결합니다.
And we can copy and paste the same node because we're going to need that for insertion as well.
정지에도 같은 노드가 필요하니, 복사해서 하나 더 만들어 둡니다.
Let's make sure that's connected.
연결 상태를 한 번 더 확인하세요.
And over here for the selection threshold, you can check the attribute value in the collection spreadsheet here.
선택 임계값(Selection Threshold)은 컬렉션 스프레드시트에서 속성 값을 보고 정할 수 있습니다.
If we go to vertices, because we painted on the vertices, you can see that the origin insertion values.
Vertices 탭으로 가보면(우리는 버텍스에 페인트했으니까) 기시/정지 값이 보일 거예요.
So, most of them are zero except the ones we painted should be value 1.
페인트하지 않은 곳은 대부분 0이고, 칠한 곳은 값이 1일 겁니다.
Let's see a few.
몇 개만 확인해 보죠.
And that means if we set the threshold to be 0.5, we should be able to get the vertex indices above 0.5.
따라서 임계값을 0.5로 두면, 0.5보다 큰 버텍스 인덱스들을 얻을 수 있습니다.
So, now we should have the origin insertion vertices.
이제 기시/정지 버텍스들을 갖게 됐습니다.
And at this point, we call compute fiber field node.
여기서 Compute Fiber Field 노드를 호출합니다.
All right, and then connect the origin insertion vertices.
그리고 방금 만든 기시/정지 버텍스들을 연결하세요.
And over here for max iteration, let's use 500.
Max Iteration(최대 반복 횟수)은 500으로 두겠습니다.
All right, now we solve for a fiber field on the lower pack and also the bicep here.
이렇게 해서 하부 대흉근과 이두근에 대해 섬유 방향 필드(Fiber Field)를 풀어냈습니다.
If you're seeing the colors are not continuous or we have a way to visualize the fiber field here,
색이 연속적으로 안 보이거나 섬유 필드를 좀 더 잘 보고 싶다면
let's go ahead and do that.
시각화를 켜서 확인해 봅시다.
So, there's our fiber field.
여기에 우리가 만든 Fiber Field가 보이네요.
Let's turn off the visualization for the spring cut drains for now.
일단 스프링 제약(Spring Constraints) 시각화는 잠시 꺼 두겠습니다.
So, if you think this is not smooth, make sure to increase the max iteration here.
만약 매끄럽지 않게 보인다면, 여기 최대 반복 횟수를 늘려 주세요.
Make sure you're using enough iteration.
충분한 반복 수를 사용하고 있는지 확인하는 게 중요합니다.
So, we just solved for muscle fiber field here.
이제 근육 섬유 필드 해석을 끝냈습니다.
And then next, let's compute some muscle activation data.
다음으로 근육 활성화(Muscle Activation) 데이터를 계산하겠습니다.
Call compute muscle activation data and then make sure we connect the origin insertion indices.
Compute Muscle Activation Data 노드를 호출하고, 기시/정지 인덱스를 연결하세요.
This will prepare us for muscle contraction.
이 작업은 근육 수축 시뮬레이션을 준비하기 위한 단계입니다.
And once that's done,
이게 끝나면,
we can set up muscle parameters.
근육 파라미터를 설정할 수 있습니다.
Let's call this set muscle activation parameter.
이 노드 이름은 Set Muscle Activation Parameter로 하겠습니다.
We'll just use the default one for now.
지금은 기본값(Default)을 그대로 쓰죠.
And let's grab the terminal.
그리고 터미널(Terminal)을 가져옵니다.
And that's everything we wanted to set up for this video.
이번 영상에서 준비하려던 작업은 여기까지입니다.
So, at this point, if we turn on muscle activation in the simulation, let's find that.
이제 시뮬레이션에서 Muscle Activation을 켜 보겠습니다. 해당 옵션을 찾아서 활성화하세요.
If you're here, do light-intubated muscle activation.
그 항목을 체크한 뒤 다시 시뮬레이션을 시작합니다.
If we have that checked, then start to simulate again.
그러면 근육 수축 결과를 볼 수 있을 겁니다.
We should be able to see muscle contraction results.
좋습니다, 방금 시뮬레이션이 끝났네요.
All right, now we just finished our simulation.
결과를 같이 살펴봅시다.
Let's take a look at the simulation results here.
보시다시피 이제 이두근이 수축하기 시작합니다.
You can see now the biceps starts to contract.
꽤 멋지죠.
That's pretty cool.
다음 영상에서는 근육 시뮬레이션을 테스트할 때 조정할 수 있는 몇 가지 옵션들을 보여드리겠습니다.
So, in the next video, we'll show you a few things that you can tweak when testing your muscle stimulation.
하모나이제이션(조화화)에 대한 부분도 다뤄보겠습니다.
have some harmonization.
작지만 유용한 컨트롤 팁도 함께 다룰 예정입니다.